<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Ryan’s Tabletop Blog</title><description>My posts about RPGs and design</description><link>https://ryanisaacg.com/</link><language>en-us</language><item><title>A Game Every Month</title><link>https://ryanisaacg.com/tabletop/game-a-month/</link><guid>https://ryanisaacg.com/tabletop/game-a-month/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;For the past couple years I&apos;ve been playing around with tabletop RPG design. My goal was to make a comprehensive hack of a game like &lt;a href=&quot;https://bladesinthedark.com/greetings-scoundrel&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blades in the Dark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://rowanrookanddecard.com/product/spire-rpg/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spire: The City Must Fall&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
but none of my attempts panned out. I found myself caught in a rut of moving from big project to big project as they collapsed under their own weight. To break the cycle, I set myself a challenge: make an RPG (or at least &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; RPG-related) every month of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;For the past couple years I&apos;ve been playing around with tabletop RPG design. My goal was to make a comprehensive hack of a game like &lt;a href=&quot;https://bladesinthedark.com/greetings-scoundrel&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blades in the Dark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://rowanrookanddecard.com/product/spire-rpg/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spire: The City Must Fall&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
but none of my attempts panned out. I found myself caught in a rut of moving from big project to big project as they collapsed under their own weight. To break the cycle, I set myself a challenge: make an RPG (or at least &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; RPG-related) every month of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;!-- more --&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set myself this goal too late into January to really get anything out there, so we start our journey in February.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;cover&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;/games/wrong-side-of-infinity&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;/wrong-side-of-infinity.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;The cover for The Wrong Side of Infinity&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;February: The Wrong Side of Infinity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started small and wrote a second draft of my one-page game &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mechanical-worlds.itch.io/on-the-wrong-side-of-infinity&quot;&gt;The Wrong Side of Infinity&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; (as well as giving its layout a new coat of paint). It wasn&apos;t even a new game, but at least it&apos;s something! This was way outside of my comfort zone; rather than piecing together parts of big indie games, I was trying to get at something pretty specific that I was feeling at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also happens to be my only Google-able game title (excluding search engine tricks like appending &amp;quot;RPG&amp;quot; to your search query). Search engine lesson for the future, I guess!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;cover&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;/games/battle-of-the-band&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;/battle-of-the-band.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;The cover for Battle of the Band&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;March: Battle of the Band&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;March saw a hack of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onesevendesign.com/laserfeelings/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lasers and Feelings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; called &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mechanical-worlds.itch.io/battle-of-the-band&quot;&gt;Battle of the Band&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;. I had the idea for a music game where you roll over or under a target depending on what &amp;quot;key you&apos;re using&amp;quot; (I&apos;m not very far in my learning-music journey but I&apos;m aware that this is mostly nonsense). Then I realized that there&apos;s already a nice, simple framework for a game with roll over and roll under. Even though it&apos;s one of many, many L&amp;amp;F hacks it was nice to get something out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;cover&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;/games/exquisite-copse&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;/exquisite-copse.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;The cover for Exquisite Copse&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;April: Exquisite Copse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My game for April was &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mechanical-worlds.itch.io/exquisite-copse&quot;&gt;Exquisite Copse&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, which ended up being my entry to &lt;a href=&quot;https://itch.io/jam/wish-you-were-here&quot;&gt;Wish You Were Here: A Postcard Jam&lt;/a&gt;. It&apos;s a letter-writing game in the style of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exquisite_corpse&quot;&gt;Exquisite Corpse&lt;/a&gt;: each person contributes to the whole, while only seeing the previous contribution, and then hopefully something interesting comes out at the end. (If you&apos;re curious, the pun came &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the game. Once I had thought of the pun I knew I had to make it into a game, somehow).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first draft was using a card prompt mechanic like &lt;a href=&quot;https://buriedwithoutceremony.com/the-quiet-year&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Quiet Year&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evilhat.com/home/for-the-queen/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;For the Queen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I dropped this because it was too many prompts for me to write in a month. My second draft, using a d66 table instead of a deck of cards, had the same problem. Additionally I couldn&apos;t decide how many prompts the players should answer; I wanted the game to be fast enough that you could conceivably play it at a party. In the end I settled on three D6 tables to produce a prompt: hopefully enough to spark the imagination while still comfortably fitting on a postcard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;cover&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;/games/a-hole-in-the-mirror&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;/a-hole-in-the-mirror.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;The cover for A Hole in the Mirror&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;May: A Hole in the Mirror&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://itch.io/jam/mock-cover-jam&quot;&gt;Mock Cover Jam&lt;/a&gt; caught my attention, so I grabbed a premade cover and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mechanical-worlds.itch.io/a-hole-in-the-mirror&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Hole in the Mirror&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; became my May game. This was interesting, because like April&apos;s game I had to start with a title and work backwards towards the game, but &lt;em&gt;unlike&lt;/em&gt; April&apos;s game I had a lot of leeway in where to go. I couldn&apos;t decide whether the title should be thematic (where a mirror is a stand-in for self-image) or literal (where a mirror is sort of a portal between worlds).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thematic approach made me think of &lt;a href=&quot;https://magpiegames.com/masks/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Masks: A New Generation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a game about teenage superheroes and their self-image. In the game, conditions aren&apos;t physical injuries but are instead negative emotions like Afraid or Angry. Your character can &apos;clear&apos; the condition by leaning into dramatic teenage behavior, like lashing out or running away. At the start of this project I thought about combining this mechanic with the push-and-pull of the No Dice No Masters token economy, where players would be encouraged to make bad decisions to enable their future successes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I picked at the core idea, I realized it reminded me more and more of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://rowanrookanddecard.com/product/the-resistance-toolbox/&quot;&gt;Resistance system&lt;/a&gt;, which powers &lt;a href=&quot;https://rowanrookanddecard.com/product/spire-rpg/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spire: The City Must Fall&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://rowanrookanddecard.com/product/heart-the-city-beneath-rpg/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heart: The City Beneath&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Specifically I thought of &lt;a href=&quot;https://gshowitt.itch.io/sepulchre&quot;&gt;Sepulchre&lt;/a&gt;, Grant Howitt&apos;s one-page stripdown of &lt;em&gt;Spire&lt;/em&gt;. It takes Fallout (the mechanic for setbacks and injuries) and turns it from a random event to a player choice. There&apos;s a kind of mechanical parallel between choosing to take Fallout and making a Weak Move in &lt;a href=&quot;https://buriedwithoutceremony.com/dream-askew&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dream Askew&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I made one other major deviation from most other Resistance games: removing the &amp;quot;damage dice&amp;quot; you roll on a success or failure, to determine how much stress you take or deal. Personally, it feels bad to roll a success then roll a 1 for my progress. Instead you roll a simple D6 pool to determine both how much progress you made and how much stress you incured while doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had more time, I would have expanded a lot more on the types of player characters and the world around them. A short chapter on setting was cut entirely, leaving just the barebones pitch: the players are fae from a mirror dimension crossing over into ours to commit crimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Takeaway&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just going through the process of making little things that I can complete in a month has been great for my creative process. It&apos;s also helped me embrace simpler, smaller games than I had been trying before. (I think my fondness for D6 is pretty clear, though I can see card-based or diceless games in my future).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flipside, however, is that I can&apos;t keep at it! Making a game every month is a lot of work. I started out strong and jumped into each new game with zeal, but by May I found myself working more out of a sense of obligation than joy. After I released &lt;em&gt;A Hole in the Mirror&lt;/em&gt;, I decided to pump the brakes. &amp;quot;Make a game every month&amp;quot; became an experiment for the spring, instead of a year-long goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if I could keep going, I want to be able to take a bit more time with my work. Most of these games are lightly proofread and barely playtested, if at all. None have any art to speak of, and the only layout is my own fumbling with Affinity Publisher. Without the self-imposed pressure of the month&apos;s deadline to throw something up online, hopefully I can strike a balance between never shipping and putting out unfinished work. For example, I do think that the core mechanic behind &lt;em&gt;A Hole in the Mirror&lt;/em&gt; has legs, and could maybe support a much larger and more intricate game. We&apos;ll see!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Going Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, the original reason I stood up this blog was to talk about this project. But now that I&apos;m here, I&apos;m really liking the idea of putting up game design thoughts on a regular basis. Probably at some point I&apos;ll set up a Twitter because that&apos;s where the people are, but I like having my own little place to put things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you soon, hopefully, with progress updates on a slower project!&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Rewriting Fellowship&apos;s &apos;Get Away&apos;</title><link>https://ryanisaacg.com/tabletop/fellowship-getaway/</link><guid>https://ryanisaacg.com/tabletop/fellowship-getaway/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This year I&apos;ve been playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://liberigothica.itch.io/fellowship-a-tabletop-adventure-game&quot;&gt;Fellowship 2e&lt;/a&gt;, a fantasy adventure RPG that&apos;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://apocalypse-world.com/&quot;&gt;Powered by the Apocalypse&lt;/a&gt;, and I have a few gripes with an otherwise great game. Since session 1, I&apos;ve felt like the core move Get Away needs re-writing, and I decided to take a stab at it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This year I&apos;ve been playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://liberigothica.itch.io/fellowship-a-tabletop-adventure-game&quot;&gt;Fellowship 2e&lt;/a&gt;, a fantasy adventure RPG that&apos;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://apocalypse-world.com/&quot;&gt;Powered by the Apocalypse&lt;/a&gt;, and I have a few gripes with an otherwise great game. Since session 1, I&apos;ve felt like the core move Get Away needs re-writing, and I decided to take a stab at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;!-- more --&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The contents of this post are licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA&lt;/a&gt;. The excerpt from Fellowship is used under the same license.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relevant move:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you need to get somewhere out of reach or out of sight, tell us where you&apos;re going and roll +Grace. If you have the Clumsy tag, you take -1 to Get Away. On a 10+, choose two. On a 7-9, choose one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get there quickly, avoiding any harm along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get there quietly, drawing no attention.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You grab someone nearby and bring them along with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two things bother me. First, I think &amp;quot;You grab someone nearby and bring them along with you&amp;quot; has only been picked a handful of times in ten sessions of play at my table. It&apos;s just not very useful in most situations. The other is the move&apos;s use of &amp;quot;negative choices&amp;quot;; the player is choosing things that &lt;em&gt;don&apos;t&lt;/em&gt; happen, rather than things that &lt;em&gt;do.&lt;/em&gt; This can put the GM in an awkward situation: if you &lt;em&gt;don&apos;t&lt;/em&gt; choose &amp;quot;drawing no attention&amp;quot;, does that necessarily mean you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; draw attention? Does it depend on the situation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.gauntlet-rpg.com/t/negative-pick-lists/1867/2&quot;&gt;a Gauntlet post&lt;/a&gt; by Jeremy Strandberg, author of the upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;https://stonetop.backerkit.com/hosted_preorders/&quot;&gt;Stonetop&lt;/a&gt;, a little while ago:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you’re going to use moves that have you chose “avoid negative” options, you kind of have to assume that some players/GMs will take it one way, and others will take it another, and ask yourself if you’re okay with either interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Or&lt;/em&gt; you can make it clear via the move’s text which you intend. A few ways to do that. You can set the default in the “body” of the move and then let choices counter/add to the default. I think this works well for moves that mix and match “positive” and “avoid negative” choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I &lt;em&gt;generally&lt;/em&gt; try to avoid moves with “__ doesn’t happen” choices. I find that moves are cleaner and easier to understand when the choices are “positive” (as in: pick things that do happen, good or bad) rather than “negative” (as in: picking things that &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; happen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I thought about the move. It&apos;s not hard to imagine this being a &amp;quot;positive&amp;quot; list (as in &apos;pick things that happen&apos;, not &apos;things that are positive&apos;), at least for the first two options. The third is a little harder, but I think with a little tweaking it could work. Here&apos;s what I&apos;m running now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you need to get somewhere out of reach or out of sight, tell us where you&apos;re going and roll +Grace. If you have the Clumsy tag, you take -1 to Get Away. On any hit, you get where you&apos;re going; on a 7-9, choose one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You take a treacherous route, and take damage along the way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You leave yourself open to being spotted or trailed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You leave subtly or suddenly, with your allies behind and none the wiser. You cannot choose this option while working alone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see a few advantages. Importantly, this move is just friendlier to players. Often something that requires a character Get Away can also be Overcome (Fellowship&apos;s catch-all move for avoiding harm). Overcome&apos;s 10+ condition leaves the character perfectly fine; why not the same for Get Away? The new move also makes the outcome clear: on a 7-9, the player chooses something bad that happens, rather than taking one possible option off the table. You can either be damaged, followed, or abandon your allies. I chose to make the last option sting a little more, and also close off its use in solo scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&apos;t the only tweak I&apos;ve made to Fellowship, and I may have more to say about my ongoing game and the hacks I&apos;ve made later. For now, if you use this in your own game, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:ryan@ryanisaacg.com&quot;&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>