<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ryan.isaac.g</title>
    <link>https://www.ryanisaacg.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on ryan.isaac.g</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.ryanisaacg.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Website Makeover</title>
      <link>https://www.ryanisaacg.com/posts/new-blog-debut/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ryanisaacg.com/posts/new-blog-debut/</guid>
      <description>So www.ryanisaacg.com has a very new look, powered by Hugo and my (fairly small) fork of the hello-friend-ng theme. Partly the site will be dedicated to a bit of a professional showcase / bio for myself, but also with added blog functionality I can communicate in a more public way about my plans for my open source projects.
The State of Quicksilver that I wrote earlier this year has moved from its previous home as Github gist to retroactively being a post here, as I feel more comfortable linking to my writing in a domain that I control and can ensure the links stay live.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The State of Quicksilver Feb 2019</title>
      <link>https://www.ryanisaacg.com/posts/state-of-quicksilver-feb-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ryanisaacg.com/posts/state-of-quicksilver-feb-2019/</guid>
      <description>What is Quicksilver? For anyone who doesn&amp;rsquo;t know, Quicksilver is my 2D game framework that targets desktop and web. It is a pure-Rust library that focuses on ergonomics and simplicity.
The State of Rust (WASM) Game Development Quicksilver is part of a small (but growing) set of Rust game engines. Notable are the Amethyst project, an open-source game engine, and ggez, a LOVE-inspired 2D game framework. Increasingly it is practical to build an entire game with only the Rust toolchain: winit provides windowing, a variety of crates allow access to platform graphics APIs, rodio provides sound, rusttype for font rendering, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://www.ryanisaacg.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.ryanisaacg.com/about/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m studying Computer Science at Rutgers University New Brunswick in the School of Arts and Sciences Honors Program. My main area of experience is PC game development, and I have had internships for both web and mobile applications. Most of my side projects are written either C, Java, Python, or Rust.
Academic Experience I&amp;rsquo;m a senior at Rutgers University, completing a CS major in May 2020. I haven&amp;rsquo;t found time for an official minor, though I try take classes on linguistics and sociology when I&amp;rsquo;m able.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>